<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.1.2//EN"
    "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.1.2/docbookx.dtd" [
]>
<chapter>
  
  <title>Widget Overview</title>

  <para>Widgets are the basic building blocks of a GUI application. They are 
    the elements that you put together to make the user interface of your 
    application. There are several standard widgets that are shipped with GTK+, 
    e.g. windows, buttons, labels, status bars, etc. It is also possible to 
    define your own custom widgets if these do not fill the specialized needs 
    of your application.</para>

  <para>All widgets in GTK+ are subclasses of the <classname>Gtk.Widget</classname>
    class. The class contains properties and methods that manage the widget 
    lifecycle, states and style.</para>

  <para>The general steps to creating a widget in GTK are:</para>
  
  <orderedlist>
    
    <listitem><para>Call the constructor of the widget, i.e. 
      <code>var widget  = new Gtk.*()</code>, where <code>*</code> is a placeholder 
      for the specific widget you wish to create an instance of. For example, if 
      one wishes to create a <classname>Gtk.Box</classname> (you'll meet this
      formally in the next chapter), this would be 
      <function>Gtk.Box()</function>.</para></listitem>
    
    <listitem><para>Connect all signals and events we wish to use to the 
      appropriate handlers.</para></listitem>
    
    <listitem><para>Set the attributes of the widget.</para></listitem>
    
    <listitem><para>Pack the widget into a container using the appropriate call 
      such as <function>container.add()</function> or 
      <function>box.pack_start()</function>.</para></listitem>
    
    <listitem><para>Show the widget by calling the <function>widget.show()</function> 
      method.</para></listitem>
  
  </orderedlist>
  
  <para><function>widget.show()</function> lets GTK know that we are done 
    setting the attributes of the widget, and it is ready to be displayed. You 
    may also use <function>widget.hide()</function> to make it disappear again. 
    The order in which you show the widgets is not important, but it's best to 
    show the window last so the whole window pops up at once rather than seeing 
    the individual widgets come up on the screen as they're formed. The children 
    of a widget will not be displayed until the widget itself is shown. Since a
    window is a widget too, widgets contained in a window will not be visible 
    until the window is shown using the <function>window.show()</function> 
    function (<varname>window</varname> is a variable that is an instance of the 
    <classname>Gtk.Window</classname> class).</para>

</chapter>
